A Guide to the Jean Linden Young papers, 1945-1997
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Jean Linden Young papers, 1945-1997
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms98-022
4 boxes, 1.5 cubic feet
Jean Alice Linden was born in Detroit, Michigan, on February 15, 1922. She became a registered architect of Washington state in 1955 and established her own private practice in 1976. Her designs were almost all private residences, apartment buildings, and small commercial structures in the Seattle area. The Jean Linden Young papers consist of materials created and collected by Young during her lifetime. They include notes written as an instructor at the University of Kentucky, newspaper articles about her and her husband's architectural projects and accomplishments, information about her tenure as Secretary General of the UIFA, personal and professional correspondence, certificates of accomplishment, photographs and sketches of buildings she designed or renovated, exhibit boards, and literature about architecture in the Seattle area.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Jean Linden Young papers were donated in December 1998 by Young's daughters, Sharon Hall and Deborah Young.
Biographical Information
Jean Alice Linden was born in Detroit, Michigan, on February 15, 1922. She was educated at Wayne University (1944-1946) and the University of Illinois (B.S. Arch., 1947). She was an architectural design and illustrating instructor at the University of Kentucky (1948-1949) and a draftsperson and designer for Brock & Johnson, Architects, in Lexington, Kentucky (1948-1949). In 1948 she married Clayton Young and they moved to Seattle, Washington, in 1949. Their three children were born in 1953 (Deborah), 1954 (Lance), and 1957 (Sharon).
Jean Linden Young and her husband established a joint practice, Clayton & Jean Young and Associates Architects, in Seattle in 1954, which lasted until 1975. After their divorce in 1976 Jean Young established her own private practice. Her designs were almost all private residences, apartment buildings, and small commercial structures, in the Seattle area. She became a registered architect of Washington state in 1955.
Young was active in many architectural organizations, particularly those that promoted the place of women in the profession. As a member of the American Institute of Architects she served on the Task Force on Women in Architectural Profession (1972-1976) and the Scholarship Committee (member, 1976-1980; chair, 1980).
Young served as a member of the Board of Architectural Registration of Washington State (member 1974-1979; chair 1978-1979), and as a member of the Citizen's Advisory Committee to the [Washington] State Senate on Financial Institutions (1974-1975). Young served on the Mayor's Small business Task Force (1984) and was appointed by the Mayor to two terms on the Seattle Design Commission (1979-1980, 1981-1982). She was also appointed to the panel of Arbitrators for the American Arbitration Association (1974). From 1985 to 1989, Young served on the King County Landmarks Commission. She also did graduate studies at the University of Washington (1974-1975).
Jean Linden Young died on May 25, 1997, in Seattle.
Scope and Content
The Jean Linden Young papers consist of materials created and collected by Young during her lifetime. They include notes written as an instructor at the University of Kentucky, newspaper articles about her and her husband's architectural projects and accomplishments, information about her tenure as Secretary General of the UIFA, personal and professional correspondence, certificates of accomplishment, photographs and sketches of buildings she designed or renovated, exhibit boards, and literature about architecture in the Seattle area.
Contents List
- Quizzes and tests from the University of Illinois, Department of Architecture, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 1:1)
- School notes and drawings of Egyptian, Greek, Roman, Early Christian, Byzantium, Romanesque, French and Italian architecture, 1946 (Box-folder 1:2)
- Certificates of accomplishments, 1947-1977 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Notes, definitions, and architect's exams on heating and ventilation, University of Kentucky, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Notes, definitions, and architect's exams on plumbing,University of Kentucky, 1949 (Box-folder 1:5)
- Notes, definitions, and architect's exams on electrical components, University of Kentucky, 1949 (Box-folder 1:6)
- Notes and quizzes on steel, 1951 (Box-folder 1:7)
- Notes and quizzes on timber, 1951 (Box-folder 1:8)
- Miscellaneous professional notes, 1951 (Box-folder 1:9)
- Application for architecture license from the State of Washington, 1951 (Box-folder 1:10)
- Notes and quizzes on concrete, 1952 (Box-folder 1:11)
- Architect examination on architectural design, June 1952 (Box-folder 1:12)
- Letters about Young's design of the Civic Auditorium for "Seattle Honors Ten Young Men," 1954 (Box-folder 1:13)
- Newspaper articles about Young, 1963-1979 (Box-folder 1:14)
- Information about the Fifteenth Northwest Regional Conference of the American Institute of Architects, for which Young was co-chair, 1966 (Box-folder 1:15)
- Information about Young for an exhibit, 1969 (Box-folder 1:16)
- Young's notes and brochures of the UIFA meeting in Monaco, 1969 (Box-folder 1:17)
- "Architecture 460--Modern Theories of Architecture." Third Church of Christ, Scientist, located in Washington, D.C. Report and critique by Young, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 1:18)
- A.I.A. Environmental Workshop--"The City as a Man-made Environment," 1969-1973 (Box-folder 1:19)
- Newspaper articles about the events of the UIFA, 1969-1979 (Box-folder 1:20)
- An AIA study - "Resolution for Environmental Study," 1970-1972 (Box-folder 1:21)
- Letters of thanks to Young for working on committees and projects. 1971-1989 (Box-folder 1:22)
- Girl Scout Silver Totem Award Design, 1972 (Box-folder 2:1)
- Notes and papers of the UIFA meeting in Bucharest, Romania, 1972 (Box-folder 2:2)
- "Organization of Women Architects" brochure, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 2:3)
- Newspaper articles about events of the AIA, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 2:4)
- Papers and thank you letters about personal talks and speeches given by Young, 1972-1990 (Box-folder 2:5)
- Letters about civic committees on which Young served, 1973-1977 (Box-folder 2:6)
- Personal letters to Young, 1973-1982 (Box-folder 2:7)
- AIA Task Force on Women in Architecture, 1975 (Box-folder 2:8)
- SHE: Sisters for a Human Environment. 1975-1989 (Box-folder 2:9)
- Notes, papers, and programs from the UIFA meeting in Iran, 1976 (Box-folder 2:10)
- Information about women in the field of architecture, 1976-1981 (Box-folder 2:11)
- Letters notifying Young about appointments and nominations to committees and awards, 1976-1989 (Box-folder 2:12)
- Young's resume and list of accomplishments, 1977-1991 (Box-folder 2:13)
- Notes, papers, and programs of the UIFA meeting in Seattle, Washington, 1979 (Box-folder 2:14)
- Information about the "Delegation for Friendship Among Women," for which Young was a delegate, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 2:15)
- Information about Women in Design International (WIDI), 1980-1982 (Box-folder 2:16)
- Publications about Young, 1981-1991 (Box-folder 2:17)
- Notes, papers, and programs from the UIFA meeting in Paris, 1982 (Box-folder 2:18)
- King County Landmarks Commission-Historic Preservation Program, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 2:19)
- Notes, papers, and programs from the UIFA meeting in Berlin, 1984 (Box-folder 2:20)
- Notes, papers, and programs from the UIFA meeting in Germany, 1985 (Box-folder 2:21)
- "Old Girls Network," 1985 (Box-folder 2:22)
- Letters from the American Arbitration Association in which Young was an arbitrator, 1988 (Box-folder 2:23)
- Sand Point Community Liaison Committee: Re-use of Sand Point Naval Base, 1991 (Box-folder 2:24)
- Notes, papers, and programs from the UIFA meeting in Denmark, 1991 (Box-folder 2:25)
- Notes on the "Essentials of a Legal Contract," undated (Box-folder 2:26)
- Young's personal notes and directories for UIFA, undated (Box-folder 2:27)
- Empty folio, undated (Box-folder 2:28)
- Young's miscellaneous notes undated (Box-folder 2:29)
- "Title VII Philosophy and the New Communities," written by Young, undated (Box-folder 2:30)
- Business cards of Jean and Clayton Young, undated (Box-folder 2:31)
- "China--Eyewitness Account," written by Young about her visit to China, undated (Box-folder 2:32)
- Brochures about architecture in Seattle, Washington, undated (Box-folder 2:33)
- Photographs of houses and projects done by Young, undated (Box-folder 3:1)
- Photographs for exhibition boards, undated (Box-folder 3:2)
- Portfolio of residential remodeling for a master suite in Seattle, Washington, undated (Box-folder 3:3)
- Portfolio of the conversion of a single family residence to a pre-school at street level and apartments above in Seattle, Washington, undated (Box-folder 3:4)
- Portfolio for a residence for a family with a "wife and mother who wished to enjoy her family and guests and operate her kitchen at the same time," Clyde Hill, Washington, undated (Box-folder 3:5)
- Photographs of exhibited material by Young, undated (Box-folder 3:6)
- Portfolio for a residence for "an Oriental three generation family" in Bellevue, Washington, undated (Box-folder 3:7)
- Portfolio for activities as chair of the AIA committee on Environmental Sensitivity and Awareness, undated (Box-folder 3:8)
- Portfolio of a residence on property below street level, undated (Box-folder 3:9)
- Portfolio of residence for a businesswoman and her son in Lake City, Washington, undated (Box-folder 3:10)
- Portfolio of a non-graded private school - modular construction in Seattle, Washington, undated (Box-folder 3:11)
- Portfolio of a parent's semi-retirement apartment and boat facilities in Liberty Bay, Washington, undated (Box-folder 3:12)
- Portfolio of a bachelor's residence and work shop in Seattle, Washington, undated (Box-folder 3:13)
- Portfolio of major additions to an existing "A" frame summer cabin in Liberty Bay, Washington, undated (Box-folder 3:14)
- Portfolio of a minimum work retreat for three months of the year in Indianola, Washington, undated (Box-folder 3:15)
- Portfolio of a residence on a steep hillside in Bellingham, Washington, undated (Box-folder 3:16)
- Sketches of speculative houses in Clyde Hill, undated (Box-folder 3:17)
- Papers from an exhibit developed for the UIFA conference on the "Humanization of the Urban Environment" held in Bucharest, Romania, undated (Box-folder 3:18)
- Portfolio for stage set designed and executed for the National T.O.Y.N., for the Seattle Jaycees, undated (Box-folder 3:19)
- Exhibit of a Northwest residence (Box-folder 4:1)
- Newspaper articles about the AIA. (Box-folder 4:2)
- Needlepoint design of the Girl Scout Totem Council. 1971 (Box-folder 4:3)
- Two drawings of plans for the Church of Religious Science (location unknown). (Box-folder 4:4)